Guide to the Norman A. Hutchings Papers, 1939-1946 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Norman A. Hutchings papers 1939-1946 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Hutchings, Norman A.
1.2 linear feet Extent: 488 Items
Norman Hutchings entered the Royal Navy in 1941 and received his training on board H.M.S. Collinwood. He then served as a signalman on board the destroyer, H.M.S. Faulknor, which was involved in the Battle of the Atlantic against German submarines that preyed on British merchant ships. In 1943, Hutchings posted to the naval headquarters at Fort St. Angelo on Malta. The papers of British-born Norman A. Hutchings span the years 1939-1946, and document Hutchings' experiences during World War II serving aboard several ships in the British Royal Navy. Norman Hutchings entered the Navy in 1941 and received his training on board H.M.S. Collinwood. He then served as a signalman on board the destroyer, H.M.S. Faulknor, which was involved in the Battle of the Atlantic against German submarines that preyed on British merchant ships. In 1943, Hutchings posted to the naval headquarters at Fort St. Angelo on Malta. The collection consists of 488 items gathered by Hutchings during his World War II experience, and include correspondence, diaries, newspaper clippings, photographs, theater programs and ticket stubs, and other personal notes and ephemera. The materials are arranged in groups by format: Clippings, Correspondence, Diaries, Ephemera, Naval Messages, and Photographs.
RL.00626
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Norman A. Hutchings Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2002.
Biographical Note
Chronology List
1909 Jan. 9 Born a British citizen
1941 June Joined Royal Navy
1943 Sept. Based in Malta
Collection Overview
The papers of British-born Norman A. Hutchings span the years 1939-1946, and document Hutchings' experiences during World War II serving aboard several ships in the British Royal Navy. Norman Hutchings entered the Navy in 1941 and received his training on board H.M.S. Collinwood. He then served as a signalman on board the destroyer, H.M.S. Faulknor, which was involved in the Battle of the Atlantic against German submarines that preyed on British merchant ships. In 1943, Hutchings posted to the naval headquarters at Fort St. Angelo on Malta. The collection consists of 488 items gathered by Hutchings during his World War II experience, and include correspondence, diaries, newspaper clippings, photographs, theater programs and ticket stubs, and other personal notes and ephemera. The materials are arranged in groups by format: Clippings, Correspondence, Diaries, Ephemera, Naval Messages, and Photographs. The correspondence is primarily between Norman and his wife, Iris, but there are other exchanges with family members and friends. While the correspondence mainly details Hutchings's family home life, the seven small diaries, with daily entries written in very tiny handwriting, contain descriptions of civilian life during the Battle of Britain, as well as detailed accounts of shipboard life on the H.M.S. Faulknor and dated events such as German bombing raids in Britain. Acquired as part of the William B. Hamilton Collection of British Manuscripts.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Hutchings, Norman A.; Hutchings, Iris; Hutchings family; Great Britain. Royal Navy; Great Britain. Royal Navy -- History -- 20th century; Great Britain. Royal Navy -- History -- World War, 1939-1945; Great Britain -- Social conditions -- 20th century; World War, 1939-1945 -- Great Britain; World War, 1939-1945 -- Malta; World War, 1939-1945 -- Naval operations, British; World War, 1939-1945 -- Social aspects -- Great Britain
Detailed Description of Collection
- Norman A. Hutchings Papers, 1939-1946 and undated, (2 boxes)
  - Clippings
    One folder containing 63 items, more than half of which are comic strips. The articles include information on the Fortress of St. Angelo where Norman Hutchings was stationed on Malta as well as a few articles on naval actions and soccer highlights.
    - Newspaper clippings, 1942 Apr.-1945 May and undated, (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1939-1946 and undated
    Twenty-seven folders consisting of letters to and from Norman Hutchings as well as a few letters to his wife Iris from people other than Norman. The bulk of the correspondence is between Norman and Iris. Arranged in alphabetical order by last name of writer.
    - From Norman Hutchings (NH), 1941 Oct. 2-1946 May 14 and undated, (3 folders) (Box 1)
    - To Iris Hutchings from other individuals, 1942 Jan.-1944 Oct., (1 folder)
    - To NH from Aunt B. E. Cowell, 1941 Dec.-1945 May, (1 folder)
    - To NH from Lilian Donneman, 1942 Mar.-1945 June, (1 folder)
    - To NH from Frank Farrow, 1944 July-1945 Mar., (1 folder)
    - To NH from B. H. C. Fowler, 1944 Oct.-1945 May, (1 folder)
    - To NH from Captain Ed Godsiffe, 1942 Mar.-1945 Jan., (1 folder)
    - To NH from George Heldan, undated, (1 folder)
    - To NH from A. H. Hutchings, 1942 Feb. 2-1945 Apr., (1 folder)
    - To NH from Eric Hutchings, 1942 Jan.-1943 Nov., (1 folder)
    - To NH from Aunt Frank Hutchings, 1942 Jan.-1945 May, (1 folder)
    - To NH from Iris Hutchings, 1939 Aug. 29-1945 June 11 and undated, (4 folders)
    - To NH from Aunt Mabel Hutchings, 1943 Feb.-1945 Mar., (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - To NH from A. R. "Spots" Kelley, 1944 Apr.-1945 Oct., (1 folder)
    - To NH from Norah Kelley, 1944 May-1945 Nov., (1 folder)
    - To NH from P. J. "Mac" McCarthy, 1942 Feb.-1945 Mar. and undated, (1 folder)
    - To NH from miscellaneous, 1940 Mar.-1945 Nov. and undated, (2 folders)
    - To NH from National Bank Limited, 1942 May-1945 Dec., (1 folder)
    - To NH from Ted Newman, 1944 June-1945 May, (1 folder)
    - To NH from L. G. Waite, 1944 Nov.-1945 Apr., (1 folder)
    - To NH from Mac Westerman, 1944 Nov.-1945 Feb., (1 folder)
  - Diaries, 1940-1945
    Consists of seven diaries, each in its own envelope, with the envelopes inside two folders. The diary from 1940 provides descriptions of air raids on Britain by the Germans. The diaries from 1941 through 1945 provide details of life aboard the destroyer, H.M.S. Faulknor, in the Atlantic, as well as Hutchings's time in Malta. The diary for 1942 is very fragile; please handle with care. Arranged chronologically.
    - Diaries, 1940-1943 (Box 2)
    - Diaries, 1944-1945
  - Ephemera
    One folder consisting of 31 items, half of which are theater programs and ticket stubs originating from Italy. The remaining items consist of cards, notes, and a map of Surrey, England, which was Norman Hutchings's home.
    - Ephemera (Box 2)
  - Naval messages
    One folder consisting of seven items, mostly personal notes written on scraps of message paper commonly available to a naval signalman. One note marks the date that the defeated Italian Battle Fleet anchored at Malta.
    - Naval messages, 1943 Mar.-1943 Sept. and undated (Box 2)
  - Photographs
    Two folders consisting of 39 black and white prints, mainly a package of prints featuring scenes of Bruges. Snapshots of Norman and his shipmates on Malta are also included. Also included are the packaging materials the prints came in.
    - Snapshots of Bruges (Box 2)
    - Snapshots of Malta